Louis-Alexandre Berthier Collection, 1780-1783: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
- Series 4: Return of the French Army from Virgina to Boston, July - December, 1782, dates not examined; more than 48 packets
  - 108. Plans des différents camps occupés par l'Armée aux ordres de M. Le comte de Rochambeau, undated; more than 46 packets 46 pp 32 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39)
    - 158. Camp à Dedam, Le 2 décembre, 16 miles de Wrentham, undated; 1 item 33 x 29 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-54/55)
      Pages from the manuscript diary of a Dedham resident, Dr. Nathaniel Ames, noting the passage of the French artillery on 17 November and of the four infantry regiments on 2, 3, 4, and 5 December, are reproduced in Forbes and Cadman, I, 178. "Camp à Boston, Le 3 de décembre, 11 miles de Dedam." Although the preceding map notes a "55th camp at Boston," no plan of it is included in this series and probably none was drawn. This apparent lacuna may be explained that there was no "camp," strictly speaking, in Boston. Arriving in succession on 3, 4, 5, and 6 December, the troops were immediately embarked on ships lying in the harbor, as noted in several of the officers' journals.
      MS, No. 39-54/55. Rochambeau's copy (lacking directional arrow for the river and the designation "Meeting House") is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 193]
      For further identification of the houses, see Albert A. Folsom, "Camp of the French Army, Dedham, 1782," The Dedham Historical Register, XII, No. 1 (Jan. 1901), 8-10.
  - 150. Tableau de la marche des Brigades de Bourbonnois et de Soissonnois partant du Camp de Hunts Taverne un jour de distance l'une de l'autre our se rendre a East-Hartford, undated; 1 item 18 x 35.5 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 40)
    Field Sketch for the Map of Camp at Farmington. This rough pencil sketch of Farmington appears on the verson of a memorandum noting the timetable and distances for the march of the two brigades from Hunt's Tavern to East Hartford, 22-31 October 1782. It provides an unusual example (the only one known to the Editors) of Berthier's rapid on-the-spot notations that he later worked up into finished maps. Other such field sketches were presumably made day by day as a cumulative record of the camps and marches of the army. The training of the topographical engineers emphasized quick and accurate observation in circumstances that precluded the use of regular surveying instruments. The reconnoiterer must then count his own paces, or his horse's, to determine distances from point to point along the road. As he proceeds he must observe and note roughly on his paper "rivers, brooks, canals, bridges, fords, ravines, swamps, mountains, woods, wayside shrines, mills, gallows, and anything else he meets up with." He must sight such distant landmarks as towers, belfries, and windmills in order to establish the direction of the road. And, if time allows, he should also go up into some high building and sketch the surrounding country.
    MS, No. 40 [Rice/Brown, pp. 189-190]
    A standard textbook, Dupain de Montesson's L'Art de lever les plans, in a section entitled "Des reconnaissances militaires, ou faites à vue" (2nd edn., 1775, pp. 176-178), discusses a typical situation faced by a reconnoiterer such as that described above.
- Series 5: Return to France via West Indies (and Miscellaneous Material), 1782-1785; 6 packets
  Consists of Berthier's account of the French fleet's return to France via the West Indies 1782-1783), as well as miscellaneous notes and documents.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "Journal" or Day-book, 1782 December 22 - 1783 February 15; 1 item 26 pp 31 x 20.5 cm 15 blank pages (Portfolio II, Packet 41)
    Journal: records movement of French fleet from Boston to Porto Caballo. [Cf. No. 3]
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 41. [see Rice/Brown, v. 1, p. 256, footnote 88]
  - Notes sur la Province de Caracas, nouvelle Espagne, undated; 1 item 8 pp 34.5 x 23 cm Autograph manuscript. 2 blank pages. Folded. (Portfolio II, Packet 42)
    Notes on the Province of Caracas, New Spain
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 42. [See Rice/Brown, v. 1, p. 270, footnote 114.]
  - Indigo Plantation Expenses, 1783; 1 item 6 pp 32 x 21 cm Autographed manuscript. 3 blank pages. Contains pen-and-ink drawing of an indigo "machine." (Portfolio II, Packet 43)
    Statistical summary of the expenses of an indigo plantation, with sketch of an indigo "machine." Caracas, 1783.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 43. [See Rice/Brown, v. 1, p. xxviii. The sketch is reproduced on unnumbered page before p. 265.]
  - Découverte de la Virginie en 1586, undated; 1 item 28 pp 32 x 21 cm Autograph manuscript. 18 blank pages. (Portfolio II, Packet 44)
    Historical Notes on the Discovery of Virginia in 1586
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 44.
  - Death Certificate of Charles-Louis-Jean Berthier, 1785; 1 item 4 pp 23 x 17.5 cm Certified copy. Autograph document. 3 blank pages. (Portfolio II, Packet 45)
    Charles-Louis-Jean was Berthier's brother, who died at Curaçao on February 17, 1783.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 45. [See Rice/Brown, v. 1, pp. 261-262 and footnote 100.]
  - Letter from General Rochambeau to the Marquis de Ségur, Paris, 1785 May 30; 1 item 4 pp 20 x 15.5 cm Autograph signed letter. 3 blank pages. (Portfolio II, Packet 46)
    Letter requesting copies of Blarenburg's [i.e., van Blarenberghe] paintings of the surrender at Yorktown, which he wishes to hang on either side of a portrait of Washington. Endorsed by Ségur: "M. Berthier, m'en parler.. ." [ "Berthier, speak to me about this."]
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 46. [See Rice/Brown, v. 2, p. 161.]
- Series 6: Berthier's Journey to Prussia, 1783; 1 packet
  Consists of Berthier's account of the trip he took in Germany and Austria during the summer of 1783 to observe the maneuvers of the war machine organized by Frederick II. The manuscript indicates that he traveled alone, by post most of the time, hiring a horse occasionally to visit a battlefield. He was probably the only French observer following the military operations that year.
  Not arranged according to any arrangement scheme.
  - Voyage en Prusse du 2 Août 1783, 1783 August 2-September 22; 1 item Four "cahiers," comprising 132 pages of text Autograph mauscript. In brown slip-case. (Portfolio XIII, Packet 47)
    Journal of Berthier's Journey to Prussia.
    Old catalogue number: MS 1585.173q.
    The manuscript is described in detail by Gilbert Chinard in "Alexandre Berthier's "Voyage en Prusse," in The Princeton University Library Chronicle, Volume V, No. 3 (April 1944), pp. 92-103. English translations of a number of Berthier's entries are provided.
- Series 7: Additions, 1807; 2 folders
  Consists of additional manuscript material related to Louis-Alexandre Berthier.
  Arranged in accession number order.
  - AM 12440: LS to Bernard Germaine de Lacépède, 1807 May 18; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AM 19755: "Rapport fait au premier Consul par le Ministre de la Guerre", undated; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 2)